There was another development in the
news that I think
bears some conversation. Congressman Ro
Khanna, who is a progressive Democrat
from northern California, went to Israel
this week and immediately ran into
trouble.
When the US gets back into negotiating
in good faith with Iran, the biggest
hurdle
is likely to be getting Israel to
to cease its military operations in
Lebanon as well as Syria.
There was this major development around
that issue that included Ro Khanna.
I want to say before I talk about Ro
Khanna that Donald Trump has been
surprisingly consistent
in his opposition to the Israelis
continuing military operations in
Lebanon and Syria. Trump just doesn't
understand why the Israelis are doing
it, at least not on the scale at which
they're doing it. I've said in podcasts
in the past
that if the Israelis want to target one
single target let's say there's a
Hezbollah leader
who lives in some apartment the Israelis
will blow up the entire apartment
complex. They'll take out the entire
city block
kill hundreds of people if they believe
they're going to be able to get this
Hezbollah commander.
That's a long-standing Israeli policy.
It's also a war crime.
You can't specifically target civilians
and that's essentially what they do.
Well
not only are they doing the same kind of
thing in Syria on a smaller scale than
what they're doing in Lebanon, but
they're doing something else in Syria
that runs
in conflict with American policy. Now,
American policy was
to force Bashar al-Assad out of power.
That happened. Bashar al-Assad fled to
Moscow and he's living privately,
secretly in Moscow with as much as he
could steal.
So, the new president
of Syria, who used to be
you know, he was one of the co-founders
of ISIS. He was an Al-Qaeda commander.
He was probably a CIA source. He was
definitely a Turkish intelligence
source. He's now the president of Syria.
And the US immediately recognized his
government. We are in the process of
reopening our embassy in Syria
with the idea that everybody's going to
live happily ever after. One of the
things that is important to the US,
whether it was during the Biden
administration or the Trump
administration, is that minority
communities in Syria be protected. And
what that primarily means is Christian
communities in Syria. There's a large
number of um Syrian Orthodox Christians.
There's still a small Jewish community,
and there's a huge Druze community in
southwestern Syria.
And the new president uh Julani has
promised to protect them. He has had
some problems keeping that promise. But
on top of
on top of the trouble of just, you know,
uprisings across the country and
continuing to fight ISIS and and to
fight uh
um other insurgents, he has to worry
about the Israelis bombing or the
Israelis crossing the border with ground
troops.
And Donald Trump
has repeatedly told the Israelis, "Stop
attacking Syria." And they won't stop
attacking Syria, just like they won't
stop attacking Lebanon. Now, in Lebanon,
of course, there is a real Hezbollah
threat to the Israelis. But the
Israelis, you know, as is their want,
tend to overreact, and they kill a lot
of civilians. Okay, enter Ro Khanna.
Ro Khanna, as I said, is is progressive
Democratic congressman from Northern
California.
He went to Israel uh this past week and
ran into some trouble. So, let's take a
look at his tweet and then we're going
to look at a very short, it's only
3-second video. He tweeted, "Israeli
settlers brandishing American-made M4s
detained me and other Americans on my
trip to Palestine."
When the IDF arrived, the Israel Defense
Force arrived, they sided with the
settlers and continued
They made a huge mistake. You will be
hearing more soon." And then he links to
a New York Times article about the
incident.
And here's the video. It's very short,
it's only 3 seconds. We've looped it,
but uh you can see the IDF is there and
they're doing nothing. He went on to say
that when his translator said, "These
are Americans. They're on a visit
sponsored by the by the American
Embassy. It is an official US government
visit and one of the men in the car is a
member of Congress."
The settlers and the IDF laughed at him.
They laughed at him.
I'm going to tell you why this is going
to be a problem for the Israelis. First
of all, most of these settlers are
Americans. They're American citizens.
They're going to need to be reined in.
Second,
official US foreign policy is to oppose
the expansion of settlements.
Most presidents are weak
in the face of the Israelis and
expanding settlements, but official
policy is to oppose settlements.
But where they really screwed this up
is detaining a member of Congress.
Ro Khanna has a vote on the budget
like every member of Congress does.
And
he can
cast his vote against
military or civilian aid to Israel.
You've probably heard Benjamin Netanyahu
in the past couple of days saying he's
going to wean Israel off
aid from the US. Great.
We should have cut off that aid decades
ago. Israel is a first-world country
with a robust and advanced economy. It
doesn't need welfare from the United
States to finance their socialist
government, which is really what it is.
Everybody gets free everything in
Israel. If you are a settler, you get a
free house, you get free furniture, you
get free utilities, you get everything
free.
We don't have that in the United States.
They have socialized medicine. It's all
free.
So, why are American taxpayer dollars
going to support this socialist uh
system in Israel? It's wrong.
But, Ro Khanna
has the ability to affect the budget, to
amend the budget, or at least to offer
amendments, and essentially to block aid
to uh to Israel if he can gather enough
uh um concurrent votes.
In the Senate, it's actually easier
because
um senators have an ability to put a
hold on on a bill, including a budget
bill. And um and they can block that
aid. Now, Ro Khanna made a statement.
We've got it on video. And uh JB, if we
can cut to that.
>> I saw the arrogance in the eyes of those
settlers. 21 and 22-year-olds with guns
laughing that they had detained us. The
arrogance of those young IDF soldiers
that my tax dollars are funding.
Having no respect for the fact that they
were detaining Americans. No respect
that there was an American
Congressperson in that bus.
And laughing when our translator told
them that there are Americans, they're
in the American Embassy as concerned.
It is the arrogance of power.
Of a power that has had no
accountability.
Total impunity. And has created a toxic
culture of oppression.
>> So, let's talk about that. President
Trump told uh Israeli Prime Minister
Netanyahu this past week uh on Thursday,
actually,
quote, "They don't want you in Syria.
You should redeploy." Unquote. As I
said, Trump has been very consistent on
this position. A senior White House
official added that the same was true in
Lebanon.
"We don't want you in Lebanon. It's a
constant problem." So, here's the
problem with that. Israel
is going to have national elections in
October, and it's hard to imagine
Netanyahu agreeing to withdraw before
October because it's going to make him
look weak.
Even if he wanted to withdraw,
members of his governing coalition, and
they know who they are,
Itamar Ben-Gvir and is and uh Smotrich,
members of this coalition are even more
hawkish and further to the right than
Netanyahu is. Some have openly argued
that Israel should maintain an
indefinite military presence in Syria,
in Lebanon, and in the West Bank and
Gaza permanent.
With some even advocating for new Jewish
settlements,
much like those established in the
occupied West Bank. Can you imagine?
Jewish settlements
in Syria and Lebanon. Unprecedented.
Getting back to Ro Khanna,
he's taken some heat on the likes of of
X, for example, or in the conservative
media saying that this was a stunt, that
it was set up.
And the reason why this criticism is now
coming fast and furious is because Ro
Kha- Ro Khanna is is heavily rumored to
be a 2028 Democratic presidential
candidate.
Um I'll tell you what it has done.
If you look at uh Cal shy, the the
predictive app, um it has moved Ro
Khanna from, you know, number 66 of
potential Democratic presidential
candidates up into the top 10.
Uh it's given him a platform. It's given
him a name.
And the more that people criticize him
and say that he set it up, the more his
name is out there, the more he's able to
to establish this position, his position
on Israeli uh settlements and uh and
expansion,
and it makes him a serious person.
So, that is something that bears
watching. It's something that we're
going to keep our eye on, certainly.